A Finding Aid to the George Nakashima Papers, 1950-1991, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
George Nakashima papers
1950-1991
Archives of American Art
Nakashima, George, 1905-1990
AAA.nakageor
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The papers of architect, craftsman, woodworker, and furniture designer George Nakashima measure 1.0 linear foot and date from 1950 to 1991. The collection is comprised of biographical material, correspondence, writings, subject files, and printed material that mostly relate to Nakashima's work in furniture design.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated by Marion Nakashima, widow of George Nakashima, in 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Biographical / Historical
George Nakashima (1905-1990) was a Japanese American architect, craftsman, woodworker, and furniture designer in New Hope, Pennsylvania. He was born in Spokane, Washington and received a bachelor's degree in architecture from the University of Washington in 1929. He also earned a master's degree from Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1930.
After his studies, Nakashima traveled around the world by steamship. He spent time in France, North Africa, and Japan. While in Japan, he began working under architect Antonin Raymond. When Raymond's architecture company was commissioned to build for the Sri Aurobindo ashram in Puducherry, India, Nakashima became the onsite architect as well as a devotee of Sri Aurobindo. When World War II began, Nakashima returned to the U.S. with his wife, Marion, whom he met in Japan. George, Marion, and their infant daughter Mira were sent to a Japanese internment camp in Idaho in 1942. The Nakashimas were able to leave the camp after Raymond sponsored their release in 1943. Nakashima began working on Raymond's farm in Bucks County, Pennsylvania, where he eventually built his workshop. Nakashima's son Kevin was born after the family relocated to Pennsylvania.
Nakashima's design work includes furniture lines for the Widdicomb Furniture Company and Knoll Furniture, and 200 pieces of furniture commissioned by Nelson Rockefeller. He also wrote a book titled The Soul of a Tree: A Master Woodworker's Reflections.
Nakashima died in 1990.
Scope and Contents
The papers of architect, craftsman, woodworker, and furniture designer George Nakashima measure 1.0 linear foot and date from 1950 to 1991. The collection is comprised of biographical material, correspondence, writings, subject files, and printed material that mostly relate to Nakashima's work in furniture design.
Biographical materials consist of a curriculum vitae and obituaries. Correspondence is with clients, colleagues, and friends in the United Staes, Japan, and the Sri Aurobindo community. Writings by and about Nakashima include articles, essays, and a speech about his design processes. Subject files are on Alfred Caldwell, flush toilet systems, trademark, and wood and tree services. Printed material includes art reproductions, booklets, catalogs, clippings, and publicity material.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as five series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1990 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1950-1990 (Box 1; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1953-1989 (Box 1, 2 folders)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1957-1980s (Box 1, 4 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1954-1991 (Box 1, 0.2 linear feet)
Artisans; Asian American art; Asian American artists; Asian American architects; Decorative arts; Woodworkers; Japanese American art; Japanese American artists; Furniture designers--Pennsylvania--New Hope; Asian American woodworkers; Asian American furniture designers; Japanese Americans -- Forced removal and internment -- 1942-1945; Handicraft; Caldwell, Alfred, 1903-1998
- Biographical Material, 1990; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Nakashima's curriculum vitae, a memorial service bulletin, and photocopies of his obituaries.
  - Biographical Material, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1950-1991; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1
  This series consists of general chronological files and named files. Chronological correspondence spans four decades and includes letters with clients, colleagues, and friends regarding business dealings, visits to Nakashima's workshop, and his ongoing affiliation with the Sri Aurobindo community. Named files are for awards, an exhibition at the Central Bucks Chamber of Commerce, correspondents in Japan, scholar and Sri Aurobindo devotee Vasant Merchant, correspondence regarding Nakashima's book titled The Soul of the Tree: A Woodworker's Reflections, and letters from the Sri Aurobindo temple.
  - General, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1950-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1961-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General (Holiday Greeting Cards), circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1982 January-May; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General, 1982 June-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General, 1985-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12-17)
  - General, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Awards, Regarding, 1982-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes material on the Order of the Sacred Treasure awarded by the Emperor of Japan and the Altar for Peace.
  - Central Bucks Chamber of Commerce Exhibition, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Japan, circa 1963-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Merchant, Vasant, 1982-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - The Soul of the Tree: A Woodworker's Reflections, Regarding, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sri Aurobindo Matrimandir, 1965-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
- Writings, 1953-1989; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 1
  Writings by Nakashima include essays and a speech delivered to the New York Herald Tribune Forum on his design process and how his craft is connected to the natural and spiritual world. Writings about Nakashima include a translated article from Kateigaho magazine, "A Tree of Destiny" by Richard A. Ek, and article excerpts printed onto a single page.
  - By Nakashima, 1953; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - About Nakashima, 1978-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Subject Files, 1957-1980s; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  This series contains mainly printed materials but also contains some correspondence and photographs in files for architecture professor Alfred Caldwell, flush toilet systems, trademarks, and wood and tree services.
  - Caldwell, Alfred, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes a speech transcript and photocopy of "The Hex of Harmony" by Caldwell.
  - Flush Toilet Systems, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Trademark, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Includes an engraving copy of a hand drawn logo for Nakashima's business.
  - Wood and Tree Services, circa 1960-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Includes photographs of cut trees, tables, and clocks.
- Printed Material, 1954-1991; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Art reproductions of St. James in Pennington, New Jersey, booklets, catalogs and clippings relating to Nakashima, and publicity material for exhibitions and events are in printed materials.
  - Art Reproductions, circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Booklets, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Catalogs, Furniture, circa 1960-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Clippings, 1954-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
    Almost all newspaper clippings are photocopies.
  - Publicity, Exhibitions and Events, 1963-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)